Boker tov, today's daf is נ"ט Nun Tes 59. We are one
daf into the fifth פרק perek תמיד נשחט Tamid Nishchat but really
into the major middle section of פסחים Pesachim which is a good
50 דף daf roughly equal in size to the rest of פסחים
Pesachim and this one could easily have come from סדר קדשים. Seder
Kodashim. It's really all about קרבנות Korbanos and about the bringing of
the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So we begin yesterday and we saw
the issue that normally the קרבן תמיד Korban Tamid the afternoon
sacrifice—there's one in the morning, one in the
afternoon—is normally slaughtered at what's called 8.5 hours which means 2:30 PM
and it's then you flay it and you dismember it and then
it's burnt on the מזבח Mizbeach at 9.5 at 3:30 PM so
roughly the middle of the afternoon. But on ערב פסח Erev Pesach
they would do it earlier because they'd need a lot of time
to bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and on ערב פסח Erev
Pesach and ערב שבת Erev Shabbos you have to not only bring
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach that day on Friday but you have
to roast the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on Friday as well because
you can't roast it at night on שבת. Shabbos. So they would
do it yet earlier still. The earliest they would do it would
be
6.5 hours mean 12:30 PM because the afternoon תמיד Tamid has to
be brought in the afternoon. We know that's the earliest we can
daven מנחה Mincha is 12:30 PM. That's assuming a perfect day, sunrise
at 6, sunset at 6. We know that the day is divided
into 12 equal units from sunrise to sunset. Anyway the assumption there
is that the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach comes after the afternoon תמיד
Tamid although the general rule is that nothing no קרבן Korban comes
after the afternoon תמיד. Tamid. The afternoon תמיד Tamid is the last
of the קרבנות. Korbanos. So that is the point that we ended
with yesterday. We'll pick up with that again at the very bottom
of נ"ח עמוד ב' Nun Ches Amud Beis two lines from the
bottom. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan our Rabbis taught תמיד קודם לפסח Tamid
kodem l'Pesach the תמיד Tamid comes before the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
the afternoon תמיד Tamid פסח קודם לקטורת Pesach kodem l'ketores and that
comes before now in the afternoon after bringing all the קרבנות Korbanos
you wouldn't be done because you would have two things still to
do. You would burn the
incense. There was incense that was burnt חצי chatzi in the morning
and חצי chatzi in the afternoon and you would also light the
נרות neiros on the מנורה. Menorah. Both the burning of the incense
and the lighting of the
נרות neiros were things that related to the קודש Kodesh not just
the עזרה Azarah the outer courtyard but the inner היכל. Heichal.
So first you do the תמיד Tamid then you do the פסח
Pesach and then you do the remaining two things. פסח קודם לקטורת
Pesach kodem l'ketores the קטורת ketores which was brought every day and
והקטורת קודמת לנרות v'haketores kodemes l'neiros the incense comes before the נרות
neiros which were lit every night. So now we're going to have
to see how we know any of this because until now we've
been certainly assuming that as far as קרבנות Korbanos are concerned the
תמיד Tamid is the last. So top of נ"ט עמוד א' Nun
Tes Amud Aleph יאוחר דבר שנאמר בו בערב ובין הערבים Ye'achar davar
shene'emar bo ba'erev u'vein ha'arbayim set to come later a thing of
which it is said בערב ba'erev and בין הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. What
does it say by פסח? Pesach? It says תשחט את הפסח בערב
Tishchat es haPesach ba'erev so
it says you do it at the night and it says ושחטו
אותו כל קהל עדת ישראל בין הערבים. V'shachatu oso kol kehal adas
Yisrael bein ha'arbayim. So
two things that refer to the afternoon or the evening period. So
ערב Erev by the way is not night it's the darkening the
end of the day the late afternoon.
בין הערבים Bein ha'arbayim means between the two ערבים erevs because ערב
Erev also comes from the word מערב ma'arav like the west. And
afternoon the ערב erev begins because the sun begins to set and
it starts moving towards the מערב. ma'arav. So that's the beginning of
the evening it's the beginning of the setting and then when it
actually sets and it actually dips below the western horizon that's the
other ערב erev and that's בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim is between the
two ערבים erevs between the moving off of the center at noon
beginning to set at noon and between sunset so that entire afternoon
period is בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim between the ערבים. erevs. So ערב
Erev is the darkening the beginning of the darkening of the day
and then לילה Layla is night. It's important to note that because
a very important רשב"ם Rashbam at the very beginning of the תורה
Torah says that the general way we read ויהי ערב ויהי בוקר
יום אחד Vayehi erev vayehi voker yom echad there was night and
there was day one day he says that's really not the פשט.
pshat. The פשט pshat is ויהי ערב vayehi erev which is it's
the
darkening which means like the sun set ויהי בוקר vayehi voker and
then it was daybreak יום אחד. yom echad. אחד, echad, so one
day was completed when the daybreak of the next day began. So
actually that it's a day that this is what would be a
more natural day rather than a halachic day, where the day precedes
the night. So things were created in the day, then the sun
set, ויהי ערב, Vayehi erev, then ויהי בקר, vayehi voker, it rose
on the next day and that completed the previous day. So ערב
erev and בקר boker are different than יום yom and לילה. laila.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara here says, ואוחר דבר שנאמר בו בערב
בין הערבים. v'uchar davor shene'mar bo ba'erev bein ha'arbayim. By פסח Pesach
it says both terms: ערב erev and בין הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. So
that double emphasis of afternoon is understood to mean late afternoon. That
comes later with דבר שלא נאמר בו בערב אלא בין הערבים בלבד.
davor shelo ne'mar bo ba'erev ela bein ha'arbayim bilvad. The תמיד, Tamid,
it only says בין הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. It says, את הכבש אחד
תעשה בבקר ואת הכבש השני תעשה בין הערבים. es hakeves echad ta'ase
vaboker v'es hakeves hasheni ta'ase bein ha'arbayim. Okay, here you have בקר
boker and בין הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. So that presumably is not as
late afternoon because it doesn't say בערב, ba'erev, it only says בין
הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. So from there we learn that the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach comes later than the תמיד Tamid because it says a
double language of afternoon by the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. אי הכי,
I hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, קטרת ונרות נמי
נקדמו לפסח? ketores v'neiros nami nikdemu lePesach? So why doesn't the incense
and the lighting of the מנורה Menorah come before the קרבן פסח?
Korban Pesach? Why? Same argument. ואוחר דבר שנאמר בו בערב בין הערבים,
v'uchar davor shene'mar bo ba'erev bein ha'arbayim, by the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach it says both בערב ba'erev and בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim and
that should come later with
דבר שלא נאמר בו אלא בין הערבים בלבד, davor shelo ne'mar bo
ela bein ha'arbayim bilvad, that it only says בין הערבים, bein ha'arbayim,
which is what it says by the incense and by the נרות.
neiros. So the same argument should say we should do the פסח
Pesach even after the incense and the lighting of the מנורה. Menorah.
גמרא Gemara says, no, שאני התם דמיעט רחמנא אותו. shani hasam dimi'at
rachmana oso. There it's different because the תורה Torah excludes by the
word of אותו. oso. דתניא, De'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa,
מערב עד בקר. me'erev ad boker. It says you should light the
נרות neiros from evening till morning, till daybreak. Okay, תן לה מדתה,
ten la mida, give it enough oil, so this is the דרשה
drasha on the פסוק, pasuk, שתהא דולקת מערב עד בקר, she'te'he dolekas
me'erev ad boker, that it should burn from the beginning of the
evening till the daybreak. That's one thing you learn out, that even
in the summer nights which are shorter, every night you have to
give it the full amount of oil that it could last throughout
a long winter night and could last the entire evening till daybreak.
דבר אחר, Davor acher, another thing you learn out, אין לך עבודה
שכשירה מערב עד בקר אלא זו בלבד. ein lecha avoda shekesheira me'erev
ad boker ela zo bilvad. This is the only עבודה avoda in
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash that goes from evening through the morning,
that goes the entire evening. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
אמר קרא, Amar krah, the פסוק pasuk says, יערך אתו אהרן ובניו
מערב עד בקר. yaaroch oso Aharon u'vanav me'erev ad boker. אהרן Aharon
and his children should arrange אותו, oso, it the מנורה, Menorah, from
evening till morning, from afternoon, from evening till morning. אותו מערב עד
בקר, Oso me'erev ad boker, this is the one, only אותו, oso,
this goes from evening till morning ואין דבר אחר מערב עד בקר,
v'ein davor acher me'erev ad boker, and nothing else. Now, somehow they're
learning although the אותו oso seems to be emphasizing nothing else runs
the entire night, the גמרא Gemara here is choosing to learn the
אותו oso also to mean that something that goes מערב עד בקר
me'erev ad boker presumably starts right before nightfall because the emphasis is
that it goes the entire night. So presumably part of the concept
of that of going the entire night means that it begins you
know very soon before nightfall and at
the end of
בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim and from there we learn from the אותו
oso that only this, the הדלקת נרות, hadlakas neiros, begins at the
very end of the afternoon and is intended to run the entire
night and nothing else begins that late. So that's where we learn
that this begins as late as possible in the afternoon.
And in common parlance I thought that most people when they say
בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim mean בין השמשות bein hashmashos like after שקיעה
shkia until צאת הכוכבים. tzeis hakochavim. But you're really saying the פשט
pshat here is בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim was derived from as midday
begins to wane
and as the
beginning of dusk.
Right. Right. I don't know if anybody says בין הערבים, bein ha'arbayim,
what do you mean in common parlance? Well they say בין השמשות.
bein hashmashos. Right, which is presumably the flip of בין הערבים bein
ha'arbayim because בין השמשות bein hashmashos is between the setting of the
sun, well not actually because בין השמשות bein hashmashos is only until
it gets fully dark. So actually how the word שמשות shmashos comes
there's an interesting רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam but I don't want to
get derailed with that right now. But anyway, but בין הערבים, bein
ha'arbayim, right, is in the תורה, Torah, is understood to mean afternoon,
right, yeah.
And also the דשן deshen was also all night was it not?
The דשן, deshen, yeah, but
is not an עבודה?
avoda? Well the דשן, deshen, you mean the fire was burning all
night. The דשן deshen was actually the תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen took
place right like before daybreak but the burning of it, right, that
wasn't an actual עבודה avoda but it is true the אש תמיד
es tamid has to be burning. Yeah, it's an interesting question anyway
what the גמרא Gemara means we'll see in a minute. I mean
you know the אמורים emurim could be burnt during the night. Exactly.
So you know but right, so it's a little question what it
means that this is the only thing that goes throughout the night.
But anyway the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it here means
that this one begins right before nighttime and therefore this comes the
latest.
Okay. ואיקיש V'ikish
קטרת לנרות, ketores l'neiros, and קטרת ketores are linked to נרות neiros
because as we'll see in a minute it says that you you
know that you
that you burn the קטורת Ketoret and you light the נרות nerot
are said in the same פסוק. pasuk. So from there we learn
that these two occur near the same time. They both occur near
the end of the day. So פסח Pesach comes after the תמיד
Tamid because it has a double language of afternoon, and נרות nerot
and קטורת Ketoret come together at the end because of the idea
of going throughout the night, at least that's the idea of the
נרות, nerot, so therefore starting near the end of the day. Okay,
then the גמרא Gemara says, however, you know what, הא תניא קושיא,
ha tanyia koshya, we do have a ברייתא Baraisa however that is
like the question you were asking, meaning doesn't answer the question but
actually embodies the question you were asking. You who were saying, you
know, let the פסח Pesach come after the נרות nerot and the
קטורת. Ketoret. So actually there's a ברייתא Baraisa that actually agrees with
your question, actually says that's exactly what you do. What does the
ברייתא Baraisa say? תמיד קודם לקטורת, Tamid kodem le-Ketoret, the תמיד Tamid
comes before the קטורת. Ketoret. קטורת קודמת לנרות, Ketoret kodemet le-nerot, and
the קטורת Ketoret comes before the נרות nerot because the נרות nerot
are as late as possible. But then it says ונרות קודמין לפסח.
ve-nerot kodmin le-Pesach. Thank you, the נרות nerot come before the פסח.
Pesach. The פסח Pesach is the very latest thing. Why? והוא דדרש
שנאמר בערב ובין הערבים ללמד שכל דבר שלא נאמר בו אלא בין
הערבים בלבד. ve-hu de-darash shene'emar ba-erev u-vein ha-arbayim lilmod she-kol davar she-lo
ne'emar bo ela bein ha-arbayim bilvad. For this logic, that the פסח
Pesach has a double language of afternoon and therefore the פסח Pesach
comes as the very latest. Okay,
so now we have those two opinions whether פסח Pesach certainly comes
later than the תמיד. Tamid. Does it even come later than the
נרות nerot and the קטורת? Ketoret? So the גמרא Gemara says והא
כתיב אותו. ve-ha ketiv oso. But according to this, you just gave
such a good answer before. You said that the נרות nerot came
last because it had אותו, oso, only then, only it, the מנורה
Menorah is at the, you know, very end. So how can here
you say the פסח Pesach comes later? The גמרא Gemara says האי
אותו מיבעי ליה. hai oso miba'ei lei. No, you need that למיעוטי
עבודה שבפנים, le-miutei avodah she-bifnim, meaning to tell you, yes, the נרות
nerot come the latest, but not the latest of everything, the latest
of the services that are done inside, meaning in the היכל. Heichal.
Right, the היכל Heichal was where you had the מנורה Menorah and
the שלחן Shulchan and the golden
מזבח. mizbeach. It was literally בפנים bifnim because it was under a
roof, whereas the most of the stuff you did was in the
outer courtyard, the עזרה, Azarah, which was open air. Okay, so yes,
the נרות nerot come at the end, nothing comes after the נרות
nerot in terms of the services done בפנים, bifnim, inside the היכל.
Heichal. ומאי ניהו? u-mai nihu? What's the other service done in the
היכל Heichal at the end of the day? קטורת, Ketoret, the burning
of the incense. So between those two, the נרות nerot come later.
סלקא דעתך אמינא. salka daitach amina. Now why would I have thought
that the incense comes later? I would have thought to say that
והא דכתיב, ve-ha de-ketiv, the verse says ובהעלות אהרן את הנרות בין
הערבים יקטירנה. u-ve-haalos Aharon es ha-neros bein ha-arbayim yaktirenah. And here's you're
going to see the combination of the נרות nerot and the קטורת,
Ketoret, them coming
together. ובהעלות אהרן את הנרות בין הערבים יקטירנה. u-ve-haalos Aharon es ha-neros
bein ha-arbayim yaktirenah. And when Aaron brings, lifts up, raises up the
flame of the מנורה Menorah in the afternoon, he shall burn the
incense. So it sounds like which comes first? It's a very ambiguous
verse. When Aaron lifts it up, he shall burn the incense. Which
is he doing first and which is he doing second? So אימא,
eima, I could have reasonably read that פסוק pasuk to
say: אימא נדליק נרות ברישא והדר נקטיר קטורת. eima nadlik neros be-reisha
ve-hadar naktir Ketoret. First you light the מנורה Menorah and then you
burn the קטורת. Ketoret. So מיעט רחמנא אותו. mi'et Rachmana oso. That's
what the verse said יערך אותו מערב עד בוקר. yaaroch oso me-erev
ad boker. Only it, the מנורה, Menorah, are the things that go
from the end of the day to the morning. Only the נרות
nerot go at the very end of the day. So and therefore
what it means is at the time he's lighting the מנורה Menorah
he's doing the קטורת, Ketoret, but the קטורת Ketoret actually precedes and
the מנורה Menorah comes later.
So at the same time, ובהעלות u-ve-haalos as ברישא, be-reisha, while...
While, right, exactly, the
same prepositional use.
Exactly. So what do we have now? We have that the פסח
Pesach is later in the afternoon than the תמיד, Tamid, although usually
the תמיד Tamid is the latest, because the פסח Pesach says ערב
ובין הערבים. erev u-vein ha-arbayim. We also have that the נרות nerot
and the קטורת Ketoret come at the end of the day. Number
one, they're wrapped together. It says ובהעלות אהרן את הנרות בין הערבים
יקטירנה. u-ve-haalos Aharon es ha-neros bein ha-arbayim yaktirenah. And we know it
comes at the end of the day because they are מערב עד
בוקר, me-erev ad boker, which presumably means from the very end of
the day throughout the entire night. And then the only question is
where does those two come relative to the קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach?
And the general sort of the emphasis of the גמרא Gemara is
that those come really at the end, the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
comes before them. But you did have one opinion right here that
even the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach comes after those, קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach comes as even later. Of course, as we have said yesterday
and we'll continue to say, you can't have the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach coming too late, because you gotta get all of the Jewish
people bringing the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach in a few hours. Okay?
Which is pretty impossible regardless. All right, so anyway, so that's why
the first approach really says yes, the נרות nerot and the קטורת
Ketoret come at the very end. All we're saying of the קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach is that it comes later than the תמיד. Tamid.
Yes?
In logic, reality dictates that you must light candles when it's dark.
Yeah, well but the פסוק pasuk says מערב עד בוקר, me-erev ad
boker, right? So you light them before...
but when it's dark already, what's... Right, before.
Well but you see them that's why you light them at the
last minute and you see them when you still have light and
you can see and then they'll be there for the nighttime. You
know I mean especially if you have to like fiddle with it
and whatnot right it's not just a simple flicking of a switch
you want to be able to see what you're doing. But the
other point is that also that you know basically the עבודה avodah
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was really ביום. bayom. I mean
the idea that night what you did was you burned the leftover
fats or whatnot but you don't really do a real עבודה avodah
you know that was sort of like wrap-up work. You don't really
do an
עבודה avodah at night general principle in terms of the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. But also I think just practically that's why you do
it right at the very end of day but not once it's
already dark.
No but also the קטורת ketoret kind of masks the awful odor
of all...
Right that's what the רמב"ם Rambam says in מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim
gives a very prosaic explanation about the purpose of the קטורת ketoret
as a type of an air freshener.
But you do the קטורת ketoret in the morning and in the
afternoon.
So you don't so you
do it in the morning...
So you do it in the morning so... No you do it
first thing in the morning the קטורת ketoret and last thing it's
sort of like the תמיד Tamid you do it first thing in
the morning and last thing in the afternoon the קטורת. ketoret.
So you do it
first thing...
Maybe right right and that aroma is still in the air if
that's the purpose of it. Yes.
Okay תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. I'm sorry did I... yes so תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
Did I skip a line? מכדי
אקדומי ממי michdei akdumei mimi אלא בין הערבים יקטירנה למה לי ela
bein ha'arbayim yaktirenah lamah li so what's the idea of בין הערבים
יקטירנה bein ha'arbayim yaktirenah by the קטורת ketoret which is a little
funny what the question is it's how you do it in the
afternoon. Anyway הכי קאמר רחמנא hachi ka'amar Rachmana but presumably doesn't that
seem to push things to say it should be very late? So
no here's what it's saying בעידן דמדלקת נרות תהא מוקטרת קטורת. be'idan
demadleket nerot tehei mukteret ketoret. So like we said when you are
lighting the נרות nerot the קטורת ketoret should already be burning. So
the קטורת ketoret and the נרות nerot come at the same time
towards the end of the day but the קטורת ketoret comes first
and the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach comes after the תמיד Tamid and
does it come after the נרות nerot and קטורת ketoret or before?
Not clear but the first opinion the one the גמרא Gemara seems
to underscore is that it would come earlier than the קטורת ketoret
and the נרות. nerot. Right. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now we taught
אין לך דבר שקודם לתמיד של שחר אלא קטורת בלבד. ein lacha
davar shekodem leTamid shel shachar ela ketoret bilvad. Now we've spoken about
the קטורת ketoret coming at the end of the day that's the
afternoon קטורת. ketoret. Now we talk about the קטורת ketoret at the
beginning of the day the morning קטורת. ketoret. And again it bookends
the same way that the תמיד Tamid of the morning and the
afternoon bookends all the קרבנות korbanot the קטורת ketoret comes even earlier
and later and bookends even more you know everything that happens during
that day. Okay אין לך דבר שקודם לתמיד של שחר ein lacha
davar shekodem leTamid shel shachar nothing comes before the morning תמיד Tamid
אלא קטורת בלבד ela ketoret bilvad only the burning of the incense.
שנאמר בה... shene'emar bah... no it's a ברייתא Baraita תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. Okay
it's I you know not clear where the ברייתא Baraita is from
but it's a
ברייתא. Baraita. שנאמר בה בבוקר בבוקר. shene'emar bah baboker baboker. The same
way ערב erev and בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim said the פסח Pesach
came late in the afternoon בבוקר בבוקר baboker baboker the double language
of morning of daybreak by the קטורת ketoret says that it comes
the very first thing even before the תמיד. Tamid. That comes earlier.
ויקדם קטורת דנאמר בה בבוקר בבוקר. veyikdam ketoret dene'emar bah baboker baboker.
דכתיב והקטיר עליו אהרן קטורת סמים בבוקר בבוקר. dechtiv vehiktir alav Aharon
ketoret samim baboker baboker.
So the קטורת ketoret should come early because by the קטורת ketoret
יקדם yekadem should come early because it says בבוקר baboker twice. לדבר
שלא נאמר בו אלא בבוקר אחד ledavar shelo ne'emar bo ela baboker
echad it should come prior to something that only says בבוקר baboker
once which is the תמיד Tamid right את הכבש אחד תעשה בבוקר
et hakeves echad ta'aseh baboker it only says one בבוקר. baboker. So
the קטורת ketoret comes even earlier. ואין לך דבר שמתעכב אחר תמיד
של בין הערבים ve'ein lacha davar shemit'akev achar Tamid shel bein ha'arbayim
and you have nothing that is postponed till after the
afternoon תמיד. Tamid. It's interesting word מתעכב mit'akev because in הלכה halacha
terminology we're used to the word מעכב me'akev meaning a criteria that
prevents you from fulfilling something. This is מעכב me'akev if you don't
do this it's מעכב me'akev right which means but it's from the
word of to hold back you're being held back from proceeding further.
So מתעכב mit'akev there's nothing that is sort of postponed that is
held from its performance there's nothing postponed אחר תמיד של בין הערבים
achar Tamid shel bein ha'arbayim after the afternoon תמיד Tamid אלא קטורת
ונרות. ela ketoret venerot. Okay so the קטורת ketoret comes before the
morning then you bring the afternoon תמיד Tamid the only thing you're
going to do after that is again the קטורת ketoret and then
the very last thing you do of the day as we said
is the נרות. nerot. That we've already said. ופסח. u'Pesach. פסח Pesach
is the one קרבן korban that will come after the תמיד Tamid
for the reason we said it has a double language of afternoon
so פסח Pesach comes after the תמיד. Tamid. And now we're going
to add something we haven't said yet ומחוסר כיפורים בערב הפסח. umchusar
kippurim be'erev haPesach. What let's say somebody is waiting to bring their
קרבן korban and it's ערב פסח. erev Pesach. Okay it's the fourteenth
of ניסן Nissan and this is somebody that was a זב zav
let's say or a מצורע metzora and they're not going to be
able to be fully טהור tahor and eat from קרבנות korbanot until
they bring their קרבן korban that ends their process of being ends
the purification process of being a זב zav or being a מצורע.
metzora. Okay so what would they do? Fine it's the fourteenth. You
bring your קרבן, korban, you're טהור, tahor, you'll be able tonight to
eat קרבנות, korbanot, you'll be able to eat from your קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach tonight. Wonderful. Only a little bit of a problem. Rats!
You forgot to bring your קרבן korban and they've already brought the
תמיד tamid of the afternoon. So, the normal rules should say: sorry
buddy, it's after the תמיד, tamid, you can't bring your קרבן. korban.
But if you don't let me bring my קרבן, korban, I'm not
going to be able to eat from the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
tonight, right? So I'm asking you to make an exception. Let me
bring my קרבן korban after the now that it's even though it's
after the afternoon תמיד tamid because this is the only way I'll
be טהור tahor that I can eat my קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
tonight. So the ברייתא braitah actually says: you know what, we give
the person that allowance. אלא כדתניא Ela k'detanya says מחוסרי כיפורים בערב
פסח, mechusrei kippurim b'erev pesach,
if you have to bring your קרבן korban on ערב פסח erev
pesach to be טהור tahor and you forgot to do it before
the afternoon תמיד, tamid, שטובל ושונה she'tovel v'shoneh you can bring your
קרבן korban now late after the afternoon תמיד, tamid, go to the
מקווה mikvah again
rabbinically you go to the מקווה mikvah after the final קרבן korban
of your טהרה tahara process ואוכל פסח לערב v'ochel pesach l'erev and
tonight you can eat your קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So we give
you that allowance. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר,
Rabbi Ishmael b'no shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka omer, and רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael the son of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben
Broka says: אף מחוסרי כיפורים בשאר ימות השנה שטובל ואוכל בקדשים לערב.
Af mechusrei kippurim b'she'ar yemot ha'shanah she'tovel v'ochel b'kodashim l'erev. You know
what? It's not even a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Let's say it's
I brought a שלמים Shlamim today. I happened to be in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, I had to come to ירושלים Yerushalayim anyway because I was
a זב zav or מצורע metzora and I needed to bring my
final קרבנות. korbanot. So I started by bringing a שלמים Shlamim or
something, and then I forgot though to do my bring my קרבן
korban that makes me טהור tahor until after the afternoon תמיד. tamid.
So רבי יוחנן בן Rabbi Yochanan ben who was it again? Who
said this? רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, רבי ישמעאל
בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Ishmael b'no shel Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka says: no problem, you can bring your קרבן korban after
the תמיד tamid because if you don't bring it, you won't be
able to eat from the קרבן korban you brought earlier.
You can just see some guy running in last minute, about to
close the shop.
Exactly, exactly. Wait, I forgot to. Right. But the scenario is fascinating
because the only reason this guy would have to eat his קרבן
korban is that he brought some other קרבן korban earlier in the
day. So I remembered to bring like סתם stam I had a
שלמים Shlamim I had made a vow for, that I brought. But
I was postponing going through the whole purification process. You know, sometimes
that's the way it is. The stuff we don't have to do,
we do sooner. The stuff that's whatever. And then he's running in,
I forgot. Right. So according to him, he would let him do
this after the תמיד tamid so he can eat the קרבן korban
that he had brought earlier even if it wasn't קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach.
He has another whole day to eat the שלמים. Shlamim. Right.
So the שלמים Shlamim might not be the best well, no, but
he has the day he brought it, the night, and the following
day. No, but if he brings the קרבן korban well, you could
say the example of תודה Todah or something. But if he brings
the קרבן korban the second day, he won't eat till that night.
So the שלמים Shlamim example actually wouldn't
work. Anyway, so that's the debate whether you allow for other קרבנות
korbanot as well. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. בשלמא
לתנא קמא, Bishlema l'tanna kamma,
I understand the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that gives a special allowance
to finish your טהרה tahara process, bring your קרבן korban after the
תמיד tamid for the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. יבוא עשה דפסח שיש
בו כרת, Yavo asseh de'pesach she'yesh bo kares, the positive מצווה mitzvah
of פסח Pesach that if you don't bring a קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach you get כרת kares for, that should come and override וידחה
עשה דהשלמה שאין בו כרת. v'yidcheh asseh de'hashlamah she'ein bo kares. The
מצווה mitzvah of השלמה. hashlamah. What does it mean, the מצווה mitzvah
of השלמה? hashlamah?
Yesterday we learned that the verse from where we learn that you
don't do anything after the afternoon תמיד tamid is the פסוק pasuk
of והקטיר עליה חלבי השלמים v'hiktir aleiha chelvei ha'shlamim relating to the
morning תמיד. tamid. And the דרשה drasha is השלמים hashlamim is השלמה,
hashlamah, that you should complete all your קרבנות korbanot after bringing the
morning תמיד, tamid, not after the afternoon תמיד. tamid. So the גמרא
Gemara now, what it does is a fascinating thing. It takes what
in the פסוקים psukim first of all is only a דרשה drasha
and it calls it a מצוות עשה mitzvat asseh based on a
very like, you know, מדרשי midrashic read of those words. And number
one, but more significantly, the גמרא Gemara sometimes does that, that's מדרשי
הלכה. midrashei halacha. But what the גמרא Gemara more significantly does is
it takes what in the פסוקים psukim would just have been an
indication of like סדר היום, seder hayom, like an indication of the
תורה Torah indicating the order of things, and has turned it into
a positive מצווה, mitzvah, right? You would not think that just because
the תורה Torah said, "Okay, this is the general order of things,
A, B, C, D, E, F, G." Then you could say, if
you did it out of order, does it still count or does
it not count? Fine, we can have that conversation. But you wouldn't
think like there's a positive מצווה mitzvah to do it in this
order and if I did it in the wrong order, somehow I
went against a מצווה. mitzvah. Okay? I went against the procedure and
we have to figure out if it's still כשר kosher or not.
So it's funny the way the גמרא Gemara phrases it that the
positive מצווה mitzvah of קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
overrides the positive מצווה mitzvah of doing everything before the afternoon תמיד
tamid as if that was a מצוות עשה. mitzvat asseh. The other
funny thing is that it's not like if I don't bring the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach now I'm going to get כרת. kares. If
I don't bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach now, it's called בזמנו,
ba'zmano, so what do I do? I bring the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach פסח שני, Pesach Sheini, right? So it's not so it's more
conceptually פסח Pesach is a weighty
מצווה, mitzvah, but. Or the only two. So that's what it means,
it's a very weighty מצות עשה *mitzvat asei*. Okay, but anyway so
it's funny the way it phrases it as a positive מצות השלמה
*mitzvat hashlama*, but
we
could rephrase it as saying it has these other questions, it doesn't
really fit in normal principles of something being דוחה *doche* something else,
but we could reframe it as saying that the idea is that
a פסח Pesach. *Pesach* is very weighty, so because of that we
allow, in order for someone to bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach.
*Korban Pesach*, for you to violate the normal order of things and
for you to bring your מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim*, your קרבן Korban
*korban* that will make you טהור tahor *tahor* even after the afternoon
תמיד Tamid *tamid*. That makes sense. אלא לרבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא *Ella l'Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka*,
but according to the other opinion, מה דרבי ישמעאל מאי דומה האי
עשה מהאי עשה *mah de-Rabbi Yishmael mai domeh hai asei me-hai asei*?
What makes the מצות עשה *mitzvat d'asei* of eating a קרבן Korban,
*korban*, every קרבן Korban *korban* after you bring it it says ואכלו
אותם *ve-achlu otam*, okay, that you're supposed to eat them, there's a
מצוה Mitzvah. *mitzvah* of eating קרבנות Korbanot *korbanot*. What makes that stronger
than the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* of doing things in the right order
and of not bringing things after the afternoon תמיד Tamid. *tamid*? Okay,
so okay, you have to eat your קרבן Korban *korban*, but we
also have our rules, we have our procedures, and our procedures are
nothing after the תמיד Tamid *tamid*. Why should we violate it just
so you can eat your קרבן korban *korban*? It's not like it's
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *Korban Pesach*. So that's the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s question. So אמר רבינא *amar Ravina* says רבינא *Ravina*, אמר רב
חסדא *amar Rav Chisda*, הכא בחטאת העוף תנן שאין למזבח אלא דמה
*hacha be-chatat ha-of tanan she-ein le-mizbe'ach ella damah*. We're talking that the
only קרבן korban *korban* you have left to bring in your purification
process is a חטאת Chatat *chatat* sin offering, which is always part
of the purification process, but a bird one, and a bird, you
don't burn on the altar, you just do the blood on the
altar. Why does that matter? Because the idea that the תמיד Tamid.
*tamid* comes last is based on a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of burning
things on the altar. It's learned from the פסוק Pasuk, *pasuk* at
the beginning of צו *Tzav* which speaks about making a fire on
the altar and it says, what does it say? It says יערך
*yaaroch*, no what's the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*? צו את אהרן Aharon *Tzav
et Aharon* זאת תורת העלה *zot torat ha-olah* היא העלה על מוקדה
על המזבח *hee ha-olah al mokda al ha-mizbe'ach* והאש על המזבח תוקד
בו *ve-ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo* okay, I can't remember.
Anyway, it says... Sorry.
The
פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* at the beginning of צו *Tzav* says, there it
is, it says, והאש על המזבח תוקד בו לא תכבה *ve-ha-esh al
ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo lo tichbeh*, so we're talking about the fire on
the altar, right, to burn, shall not be extinguished. ובער עליה הכהן
עצים בבקר בבקר *u-vi'er aleiha ha-kohen etzim baboker baboker*, you put on
new wood every morning. וערך עליה העלה והקטיר עליה חלבי השלמים *ve-arach
aleiha ha-olah ve-hiktir aleiha chelvei ha-shlamim*. You do the עולה Olah. *olah*,
which is understood to mean the תמיד Tamid, *tamid* of the morning,
and the חלבי השלמים *chelvei ha-shlamim* the fats. And this by דרשא
*drasha* means you do all the other קרבנות Korbanot. *korbanot* connected to
the תמיד Tamid *tamid*, right? השלם *hashlem*, ההשלמה *ha-hashlama*. But this is
all about a פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* of what you are burning on
the altar. Burning. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands that the real
problem of doing something after the afternoon תמיד Tamid, *tamid* is burning
something on the altar after the afternoon תמיד Tamid. *tamid*. But if
all you did was sprinkle the blood and you didn't burn it,
you actually did not technically violate. So that's how the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is doing. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka* didn't
really mean you can really bring a קרבן korban *korban* after the
afternoon תמיד Tamid *tamid*. What he meant was you could bring it
in a special case where all you did was וזריקת הדם *ve-zrikat
ha-dam* and you didn't have to burn it on the altar, and
that's what he allowed. Okay, so that's a bit of an אוקימתא
*ukimta* because it sounds like he was more general, but that's what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s saying and it makes this important distinction between
limiting it to burning on the altar. רב פפא Rav Pappa, *Rav
Pappa*, אמר רב פפא Rav Papa *amar Rav Pappa*, אפילו תימא בחטאת
בהמה Behemah, *afilu teima be-chatat behemah*, even if we're talking about not
just a bird, like a big animal. Okay, and that there is
a part that you have to burn on the altar. So again,
how does he allow the burning on the altar after the afternoon
תמיד Tamid *tamid*, if we're not dealing with getting you to bring
a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *Korban Pesach*? So מעלינן בראש המזבח *maalinan
be-rosh ha-mizbe'ach*. You do a trick. You sprinkle the blood and you
don't burn the rest, right, because what makes a קרבן korban *korban*
valid is the throwing of the blood on the altar. So what
about the part that now you're supposed to burn on the altar?
So you don't burn it on the altar. Now, can you really
allow a part of the קרבן korban *korban* to become פסול *pasul*?
No, so here's the trick. What you do is you put it
on top of the altar, and the הלכה *halacha* is that לינה
lina *lina*, which means sleeping, when something has passed its time and
it becomes invalid, doesn't apply
to the innards if they are on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* itself. So
you take all the fat of the קרבן Korban *korban* that you're
supposed to burn on the altar and you don't leave it on
the floor, you
put it on the altar, but you put it like on the
walk-around on the altar, you don't actually put it on the fire
on the altar, and then you don't bring it that night because
it's too late, the תמיד Tamid, *tamid* has been brought, you wait
until the next morning and after the morning תמיד Tamid *tamid* then
you'll
burn
the
fat.
Basically the מעשה הקרבה *ma'aseh hakrava* is effected with the pouring of
blood.
Yes, the blood is what makes you יוצא *yotzei* the קרבן Korban,
*korban*. And in everything else, the burning of the fats, the burning
of the limbs of an עולה Olah *olah*, are not necessary for
being יוצא *yotzei* your or fulfilling your obligation. The effect, right, what
effects the קרבן Korban. *korban* is the blood. So that's his answer.
מעלה ומלינה בראש המזבח *Ma'aleh u'malina b'rosh hamizbe'ach*. So, yeah, you're right,
you really shouldn't be able to violate this rule just to finish
your טהרה Taharah *tahara* process, to eat your קרבן Korban *korban*, but
we do it by this like work-around. We're not going to burn
anything that night. והאיכא אשם Asham *Ve'ha'ika asham*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, well what about the אשם asham, *asham*? Meaning that's about a
חטאת Chatat *chatas*. What about there's other קרבנות Korbanot, *korbanos* like if
you're a מצורע Metzora *metzora*, you need an אשם asham *asham*? Obviously
the same answer can apply once you have this trick. But okay.
בשלמא לרב פפא היינו דמעלינה *Bishlama le'Rav Pappa, hainu de'ma'alina*. Oh, so
according to רב פפא *Rav Pappa*, we know we can use the
same answer. You do the blood part and not the burn part.
Burning part, you leave that till the next morning. אלא לרב חסדא
מאי איכא למימר *Ella le'Rav Chisda mai ika lemeimar*? According to רב
חסדא *Rav Chisda*, you only allowed it because of who says we're
talking about the bird חטאת Chatat. *chatas*. Something that had no component
to be burned. But the אשם *asham*, which is necessary as the
מצורע Metzora, *metzora*, cannot come as a bird. Sometimes a חטאת Chatat
*chatas* can come as a bird in special cases, but not the
אשם *asham*. So אמרי שקרב אשמו *amri she'karav ashamo*. Okay, so according
to him we'd be talking that the מצורע Metzora *metzora* had already
brought the אשם *asham*. And the only thing left was the bird
חטאת Chatat *chatas*. והאיכא עולה Olah *Ve'ha'ika olah*. Okay, but the מצורע
Metzora. *metzora* also has to bring an עולה Olah *olah*. There's a
lot of things you gotta bring. וכי תימא עולה Olah לא מעכבא
*Ve'chi teima olah lo me'akva*, and maybe you'll say, oh, the עולה
Olah *olah* doesn't prevent you from, there's the word מעכב *me'akeiv*, prevent,
doesn't prevent you from finishing the purification process. והתניא *Ve'hatanya*, we taught
in a ברייתא braisa, *Baraisa*, רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא אומר *Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer*: כשם
שחטאתו ואשמו מעכבין אותו *Keshem she'chataso ve'ashamo me'akvin oso*, the same רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi
Yochanan ben Beroka*, you got himself in a corner. He says by
a מצורע Metzora. *metzora*, the same way the חטאת Chatat? *chatas* and
the אשם *asham* מעכבין אותו *me'akvin oso*, כך עולתו מעכבתו *kach olaso
me'akvato*.
So bringing his עולה Olah *olah* prevents him from finishing his טהרה
Taharah *tahara* process. Okay, so basically what's the question we're asking? We
don't understand how רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi
Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka* can say you can finish
your טהרה *tahara* process after the תמיד Tamid *tamid*. What allows you
to violate those rules in a normal case, not ערב פסח Erev
Pesach *erev Pesach*? So the answer is you do it without burning
anything on the altar. So one version רב פפא *Rav Pappa* is,
yeah, you bring all your קרבנות Korbanot. *korbanos* and you let the
meat and the fat or whatever on the top of the altar
and you'll do it tomorrow morning. But the other answer, who was
the other one who said this? Was it אביי *Abaye*? No,
רבינא *Ravina* says, רבינא *Ravina* says no, no, no, the only thing
he let you do is the bird קרבן Korban *korban*, the bird
חטאת Chatat *chatas*, because that doesn't have a part that's burned. But
the question is but you can't just say that because there's a
lot of components of the טהרה *tahara* process that are not just
the bird. Okay, there's the אשם *asham*, there's the עולה Olah *olah*,
so how do you still, how do you violate this rule of
not doing something later? So וכי תימא *ve'chi teima*, says the גמרא
*Gemara*, maybe you'll say בשקרבה עולתו *beshekarva olaso*, only in a scenario
where the עולה Olah. *olah* was already brought, the אשם *asham* was
brought, the עולה Olah, *olah* was brought, all that was brought earlier
and the only thing you forgot was the bird חטאת Chatat *chatas*.
That's how he'll describe this scenario. ומי קרבה עולה Olah קודם לחטאת
*U'mi karva olah kodem le'chatas*? Since when are you allowed to do
that, to bring the עולה *olah* before the חטאת Chatat *chatas*? ראשון
*Rishon*, that's first. והתניא *Hatanya*, we taught in the ברייתא braisa, *Baraisa*,
והקריב את אשר לחטאת ראשונה *Ve'hikriv es asher lachatat rishona*. So he
shall bring, this is another case of that special קרבן Korban, *korban*,
that a חטאת chatas *chatas* and an עולה *olah* at the end
of ויקרא *Vayikra*, קרבן Korban עולה ויורד *korban oleh ve'yored*, and it
says you bring the חטאת chatas *chatas* first, okay, before the עולה
*olah*. מה תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, *Ma talmud lomar*? Why does it
explicitly say first? אם לומר שתהא קודמת לעולה *Im lomar she'tei kodemes
la'olah*, if it's to mean that one case of that קרבן Korban
עולה ויורד *korban oleh ve'yored*, that the חטאת *chatas* comes first, הרי
כבר נאמר ואת השני יעשה עולה כמשפט *harei kvar ne'emar: Ve'es hasheni
ya'aseh olah kamishpat*. It says bring the חטאת *chatas* and the second
one do the עולה *olah*. So why does it have to say
ראשון *rishon*, do it first? It's implicit from the way it's being
written that it first says do this and then second do that.
אלא *Ella*, so why does it say first? זה בנין אב *Zeh
binyan av*. To tell you that this is a rule, a paradigm
for all other cases. לכל חטאות *Le'chol chatos*, any time you have
a חטאת *chatas* and an עולה *olah* coming together, לכל חטאות שהן
קודמות לכל עולות הבאות עמהן *le'chol chatos she'kodma le'chol olos haba'os imahen*.
The חטאת *chatas* always precedes the עולה *olah* when the חטאת *chatas*
and עולה *olah* come together. And the logic is that the חטאת
*chatas* is, let's say it's a case of a sin, like in
that case of עולה ויורד *oleh ve'yored*. The חטאת *chatas* first cleanses
you, cleanses you either from sin, if it's a sin offering, or
cleanses you from טומאה *tumah*, if it's part of a טהרה *tahara*
process, and then you're able to draw closer to God because you've
been cleansed and the עולה *olah* then is, you know, is.
is the gift to God now that you are cleansed and can
draw close. So the חטאת always precedes the עולה.
Isn't the חטאת usually the bird, the עולה is the meat?
So in there is a case of a מצורע where the חטאת
can be the bird. So here we've got a problem. If you
say you bring all the קרבנות and just let the meat and
the fat on the top of the altar wait tomorrow, fine, you
could say it by everything. But if you say no, no, no,
the only case that's allowed was when all that was left was
the bird, how can all that's left be the bird? You have
to do the עולה as part of the טהרה process, and the
עולה has to come after the bird, right? And the עולה always
is a בהמה, Behemah. it's not a bird. The only thing that's
a bird, it could be a bird, is the
חטאת. וקיימא לן, Ve-kayma lan, and we have the principle דאפילו חטאת
העוף, De-afilu Chatat Ha-of, even a bird חטאת which is so trivial
in terms of like, you know, its cost, קודמת לעולת בהמה, Kodemet
Le-olat Behemah, the חטאת always comes first, even a bird one before
an עולה of a בהמה. So we're back to this issue about
how do you say that all you had left was the bird
חטאת?
A bird can't be a substitute for all these other קרבנות. קרבן
עני, Korban Ani, I thought it was
sometimes
the Torah does allow for different קרבנות, you know, a bird substitute
or sometimes even a grain offering, a מנחה, Mincha, but it's only
very specific cases and it's only some of the קרבנות. So by
the מצורע, the only one it allows a substitute for is the
חטאת part, not the אשם and the עולה part.
If he was poor, he'd need to take a loan and buy
the animals that way or have his uncle give him an animal.
Basically, exactly. So the גמרא says, so אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
שאני עולת מצורע, Shani Olat Metzora, by the עולה of a מצורע
you have a little more latitude. רחמנא אמר, Rachmana amar, the Torah
says והעלה הכהן את העולה, Ve-he-elah Ha-Kohen et Ha-olah, and the כהן
Kohen shall bring up the עולה. It says this after it speaks
about him bringing the חטאת by the מצורע. Now normally it should
have said ואחר יעלה הכהן את העולה, Ve-achar ya'aleh Ha-Kohen et Ha-olah,
shall bring
up. והעלה Ve-he-elah is a funny formulation. So the דרשה Derasha is
שהעלה כבר, She-he-elah kevar, even if he had already brought up the
עולה, he can still, that's okay. The עולה could come before the
חטאת by a מצורע. Okay, so basically the rule is, just remind
us where we're up to, the rule is nothing comes after the
afternoon תמיד Tamid. except the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach What if you,
you know, as Dovid so eloquently put it, you're running wait, wait,
wait, I forgot, and you're coming and it's too late and you
still have to finish a טהרה process? So if it's for the
sake of enabling you to bring your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach that
night, to eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach that night, we'll allow
it. A קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is going to override. If it's
just to eat another קרבן Korban that night, you know, the חכמים
Chachamim say we're not going to allow it. I'm sorry, they were
closed for the day. It's after תמיד. Tamid רבי ישמעאל בנו של
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yishmael Beno Shel Rabbi Yochanan Ben Beroka
does allow it. The גמרא doesn't really understand that because the logic
is we shouldn't violate our rules just for this. And it basically
gives one of two answers. They're really the same answer. It's a
case where you just did the blood part. You did not do
the burning part. And the idea that the תמיד Tamid is last
is about the burning. Either it means you leave all the meat
to be burnt the next day, or it means a special case
that all you had to do was a bird sacrifice. But the
basic answer is you're not going to, we're not going to do
any burning after the תמיד. Tamid, Okay, so now the גמרא says
like this. אמר ליה רב שמן בר אבא לרב פפא, Amar leh
Rav Shemen Bar Abba le-Rav Pappa, so רב שמן בר אבא Rav
Shemen Bar Abba said to רב פפא, לדידך, Le-didach, according to your
way of explaining this position, דאמרת, De-amart, that you said מעלו ומלינה
בראשו של מזבח, Ma'alu u-melina be-rosho shel mizbe'ach, you bring it up
and you let it sleep overnight at the top of the altar
so it doesn't become invalid and you can burn it the next
morning, קיימין ועבדינן נוכלא לכהנים דאתו לידי תקלה? Kaymin ve-avdinan nochla le-Kohanim
de-atu lidei takalah? Are we going to get up and do something
that for the כהנים Kohanim that will lead the כהנים Kohanim to
stumble? Meaning, you know, you're asking for trouble doing this. A כהן's
Kohen going to go up in the middle of the night and
see all this meat and fat of the sacrifice, right, that's sitting
there on the top of the altar, he's going to assume what?
He's going to assume this was some stuff that was brought earlier
today, because what do you do at night? At night you do
all of the burning of the stuff that you didn't get around
to in the morning.
Or he just forgot to put the stuff on the fire?
Exactly, and he'll put it on. וסבר דיומא הוא, Vesavar de-yoma hu,
he'll assume this stuff is not supposed to wait till the next
morning. He won't know you did this trick. He'll assume it's leftover
from stuff that was brought that day. ואתי לאקטורי, Ve-ati le-akturei, and
he'll burn it. Now, of course, it is funny that it says
this is אתי לידי תקלה, ati lidei takalah, that it's going to
lead to a stumbling, because okay, let's say he did burn it.
What would he have done? He would have violated the procedure that
you don't do anything after the afternoon תמיד, Tamid. right? That's what
he would have violated, right? Because this was a קרבן, Korban, meaning
if you brought the sprinkled blood before the תמיד and you burnt
the fat after, that's not seen as a violation because that relates
to a קרבן that was done before. It's interesting. You're burning something
after the afternoon תמיד, but it's being burned for a קרבן that
relates to the earlier period. If in this case you sprinkled the
blood after, if you were to burn it, that would be a
violation of the rule of burning something on the altar that was
done after the afternoon תמיד. But that concern is like such a
תקלה, Takalah, like it sounds like some big sin, some big violation.
Again, the גמרא treats this idea of not doing something after the
afternoon תמיד as a real מצוה. mitzvah And if you... And if
you don't do it, you violated this מצוה. mitzvah So therefore, how
do we let them put in this scenario where they might come
to violate this מצוה of not doing something later? Yes.
So things were constantly being burnt after the, after the last תמיד
was brought? Oh yeah, of course, as long as they were, the
blood was sprinkled earlier.
Right, which is important to note. It's not really, it's a little
bit ironic, right? It's that the קרבן can be brought, the blood
sprinkled after the afternoon תמיד, things can be burnt after the afternoon
תמיד if it was brought beforehand. The only thing that you can't
do is burn something after the afternoon תמיד that was brought after
the afternoon תמיד. It's a very, you know, narrowly defined type of
a case.
And the reason why we allow you to to bring actually and
actually burn it on ערב פסח Erev Pesach after the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach is because we think that we want you
to, we want because we want to give you the opportunity to
do פסח.
Pesach Because as you made the
point, well, it's a כרת kares
כרת, kares, but that you could have... Yeah, but still, the point
is it's a very weighty מצוה and everybody is doing it together
tonight and so on, so we're going to make an allowance to
allow you to do this. Okay. So anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei,
so he said back to him, כהנים זריזים הן. kohanim zerizim hein.
Yeah, כהנים kohanim are very careful. They'll know not to, you know,
they'll tell one another, oh, be careful that stuff up in the
corner over there, leave that alone, that's for tomorrow. So they'll be
very scrupulous of letting one another know and of remembering not to
touch it. Okay. So אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא, amar lei
Rav Ashi l'Rav Kahana, so רב אשי Rav Ashi then said to
רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, רמי ליה רב הונא בריה דרב נתן לרב
פפא rami lei Rav Huna brei d'Rav Nasan l'Rav Papa said to
רב פפא who was the one who was the author of this
idea that you leave the fats on the top of the altar,
והא כל זמן דלא נתקטרו אימורין, v'ha kol zman d'lo niskatru emurim,
as long as the fats are not, are not burnt, כהנים לא
מצי אכלי בשר, kohanim lo matzi achli basar, the כהנים kohanim cannot
eat the meat, right? If let's say you're talking about a חטאת
or an אשם, so the fats would be burnt on the altar,
the כהנים kohanim would eat the meat, right? It's the חטאת and
אשם don't go out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's the
כהנים kohanim that eat it, not the owners. Okay, but as long
as the fats aren't burnt, the כהנים kohanim don't have a license
to eat the meat. How do you know that? דתניא, de-tanya, we
learn a ברייתא, Baraisa יכול יהו כהנים רשאין בחזה ושוק קודם הקטרת
אימורין? yachol yehu kohanim resha'in b'chazeh v'shok kodem haktaras emurim? Maybe this
is now talking about a שלמים. shelamim. By a שלמים, shelamim, the
כהנים kohanim don't eat all the meat, but the owners do, but
they get the breast and the thigh. So maybe they would be
able to eat their portion before the fats were burnt, since as
we said, the קרבן is satisfied, is done when the blood is
sprinkled, maybe they could eat their portion even earlier, even as soon
as the blood is put on the altar. תלמוד לומר, the verse
teaches, והקטיר הכהן את החלב המזבחה, v'hiktir hakohen es hachelev hamizbeicha,
it says the כהן kohen will burn the fat on the altar,
והדר, v'hadar, and only afterwards the פסוק Pasuk says, והיה החזה לאהרן
ולבניו, v'hayah hachazeh l'Aharon ul'vanav,
that אהרן and his sons get the breast from the שלמים. shelamim.
So basically and from there we learn a general rule that the
כהנים kohanim do not eat the meat of the קרבן as long
as the fats are not offered. Okay, so you've got this fat
on the top of the altar, you're not burning them till the
next morning, so the כהנים kohanim are not eating the meat of
the קרבן till the next morning. Why should that matter? Because of
point number
two. וכמה דכהנים לא אכלי בשר, v'chama d'kohanim lo achli basar, and
as long as the כהנים kohanim are not eating the meat, בעלים
לא מתכפרי, ba'alim lo miskapri, the atonement of the owners is not
fulfilled, the owners don't get their atonement. How do you know that?
דתניא, de-tanya, we learn a ברייתא, ואכלו אותם אשר כופר בהם, v'achlu
osam asher kuppar bahem,
and they should eat them, those that are being atoned through
them. מלמד שהכהנים אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים. melamed she-hakohanim ochlim u-ba'alim miskaprim. That
finishes the atonement of the owners. Now that sounds a little bizarre:
you're eating your meat, I'm getting atoned. This is an idea though
that is said many times that the eating of the כהנים kohanim
is like the eating of the altar. You know, the כהנים, kohanim,
they don't leave the temple grounds, the eating takes place in the
temple grounds, you know, they are seen as, you know, the phrase
we use even nowadays, כלי קודש. klei kodesh. To some degree they
are seen as part of the sanctified objects in the temple and
their eating is a type of a consumption being done in the
temple. Now still, even that being said, it's funny that the atonement
is dependent on the consumption of the fats or of the meat,
because you would say that again, it all goes to the blood.
And we're about to find out that yes, בדיעבד, b'diavad, even if
all you had was the blood, it's fine. But at least at
a certain stage we say, to really do it the right way
and to really get fulfillment, you need to burn the אימורין, emurim,
that gives license to the כהנים kohanim to eat the fat. That's
a concept by the way of משולחן גבוה קא זכו, mishulchan gavo'ah
kacha'u, they're getting their portion from God's table. So first God's thing
is brought, the fats is burnt, so you know, as God got
his portion as it were, then they eat their portion, the meat,
and after all that consumption, that's when the owners get their atonement.
So here's the problem: I need to bring my קרבן in order
to be טהור tahor to eat my thing tonight. We're going to
do the blood tonight, but we're not going to do the meat
and stuff till tomorrow. But then I'm not טהור because if we're
not doing the fats
and we're not doing the meat. And the
גמרא *gemara* here is saying that very literally, like really I'm not
טהור *tahor* yet until that is done. So let's see what the
גמרא *gemara* says about that. אמר ליה amar lei, *amar lei*, so
he said back to him, כיון דלא d'lo אפשר *kivan d'lo efshar*,
since it's not possible to burn the fat and eat the meat
tonight, the rabbis made it as if the meat were טמא *tamei*
or was lost, meaning if you don't have the meat and you
don't burn the fats and you don't eat the meat, then the
owners still get their atonement
if it's not able to be
done. דתניא *detanya*, like we taught in the ברייתא *baraisa*, יכול נטמאו
אימורין emurin או שאבדו לא יהיו כהנים kohanim זוכין בחזה ושוק *yachol
nitmu imurin o she'ovdu lo yiheyu kohanim zochin bachazeh v'shok*, maybe if
the fats became טמא *tamei* or they got
lost, the כהנים kohanim *kohanim* won't be able to eat the meat?
תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, והיה החזה לאהרן ולבניו *v'hayah hechazeh l'Aharon u'l'banav*,
that the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* also stands by itself, they get that
meat מכל מקום *mikol makom*, regardless. So what it's saying is, you
know what? Since you're not allowed to bring the fat tonight, so
therefore from the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*'s perspective, it's like okay, forget about
the fats, they can't be done, so therefore we're going to get
the meat even without the fats being brought, and if we're going
to get the meat, we eat the meat, the owners get their
atonement. It should also be stated that let's say not only the
fats, I say the fats and the meat became טמא *tamei*, nobody
would say the owner has to bring another קרבן *korban*. Everybody agrees
that בדיעבד *b'diavad*, if you can't do it, then certainly the owners
get their atonement just by the blood. What's
the כהנים *kohanim* full? Well, that's- well remember the דרשה *drasha*, the
אגדתא *agadeta* at the end of the last פרק *perek* about this
כהן *kohen* that was able to eat hundreds and hundreds of pounds?
So yeah, but yes, it is an interesting question how literally the
גמרא *gemara* thinks that the owners need the eating of the burning
of the fats and the eating of the meat in order to
fulfill their obligation, because there is this extremely strong emphasis that it's
all about the blood. And certainly when there's no other options, if
they became lost or טמא *tamei*, then they fulfill their obligation just
with the blood. And here what it's saying is since you can't
bring the אימורין *imurim*, that gives the כהנים *kohanim* the license to
eat the fat even immediately and therefore the problem is
solved. Okay.
Simple time they didn't
even have ברכות *brachos*?
That's a good
question. ברכות הנהנין *birkos hanehenin* is not so clear
when that got instituted. But they did have a ברכה *bracha* on
the bringing and eating of a קרבן *korban* as a מצוה *mitzvah*
of bringing and eating a קרבן *korban*.
Of course you really never know if they became כפרה *kapara*
on time.
Right, that's true too, like if you have to wait for the
כהנים *kohanim* to eat it, you know, you never know, they don't
know, right, exactly. Although you could assume by the end of the
day, again, you could work with the assumption since it's stuff that
have to be eaten by the end of the day that everything
has been taken care of. But and that is discussed other times,
like the owner's ability to assume that certain things are done as
they're supposed to have been done in the בית המקדש *bais hamikdash*.
But again, the question is does גמרא *gemara* really mean this בדיעבד
*b'diavad*, like that if they never got around to eating it you
really would have to bring another קרבן *korban*? That we don't say.
Okay, so it really is at the end of the day about
the blood. רב כהנא רמי *Rav Kahana rami*, now we'll wrap this
up by again, so that's the end of that fascinating discussion about
bringing after the תמיד *tamid* and emphasis on the burning, not the
blood, but burning only of the problem of something that was brought
later. Okay and okay, so now the גמרא *gemara* says like this.
רב כהנא רמי *Rav Kahana rami*, one more set of פסוקים pesukim,
*pesukim* about the order of things in the בית המקדש *bais hamikdash*.
כתיב *ksiv*, one verse says לא ילין yalin, חלב cheilev חגיגי עד
בוקר *lo yalin chelev chagagi ad boker*, the fat of my חגיגה
*chagiga* of my holiday sacrifice should not sleep over till the next
morning. עד בוקר הוא hu דלא ילין yalin, *ad boker hu d'lo
yalin*, so you can't let the fat wait till the next morning,
then it
becomes נותר *nosar*. הא כל הלילה halayla כולו ילין yalin, *ha kol
halailah kulo yalin*, but it can sleep through the night, you can
burn it through the night. Okay? וכתיב *uch'siv*, but the other verse
says והקטיר עליה חלבי השלמים *v'hiktir aleha chelvei hashelamim*, this is exactly
the problem that we mentioned, that you're supposed to finish all the
burning with the תמיד *tamid*, עליה השלם כל הקרבנות כולם *aleha hashelam
kol hakorbanos kulam*, before the afternoon תמיד *tamid* by the morning תמיד
*tamid* you should do all of the burnings of all of the
קרבנות *korbanos*. So how do you burn the fats at the night?
הוא מתיב לה והוא מפרק לה *hu masiv lah v'hu mifarek lah*,
he raised the question and he answered it. We're talking that it
was left over. If you brought the קרבן *korban* before the afternoon
תמיד *tamid*, then you're entitled to finish it and to do the
burning after the afternoon תמיד *tamid*. Then it's like wrap up of
what happened before. So you can wrap up what was done before
but you can't do a burning of something that was done after,
like we've been saying. רמי ליה רב ספרא לרב *rami lei rav
safra l'rav*, Rav Safra challenges
Rav, some say רבא *Rava*, he challenges רבא *Rava*, which works better
in terms of the date of Safra. כתיב *ksiv*, one פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk* says לא ילין לבקר Laboker זבח חג הפסח *lo yalin laboker
zevach chag hapesach*,
do not leave over till the next morning the... the sacrifice of
the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach? Now the simple sense of that verse
means the meat, that you have to eat the meat before the
next morning. But he understands that it means the fat, that you
can't let the fat of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach stay till
the next morning. Okay, so לבקר הוא דלא ילין, so you can't
let it stay till the next morning. הכל Hacol הלילה halayla ילין,
you can burn the fat of the קרבן פסח Pesach at night.
Now there's a little problem about burning the fat of a קרבן
פסח at night because what is the night that you are that
what is that night? יום טוב. Yom Tov. What did you say?
יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, now normally
a קרבן that's brought on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can burn
the fat on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But when did you bring
the קרבן פסח? On י"ד, Yud-Daled, on the 14th, not on the
15th. So how can you then burn the fat that
night? והכתיב, V'haksiv, the verse says עולת שבת בשבתו, Olat Shabbat b'Shabbato,
the עולת Olat שבת Shabbat on its שבת, Shabbat, ולא עולת חול
בשבת, v'lo Olat chol b'Shabbat, you cannot be doing the previous day's
קרבן, you can't burn the fat from the previous day's תמיד on
שבת, Shabbat, the Friday afternoon תמיד you can't go ahead and burn
it Friday night because that's a weekday קרבן. ולא עולת חול ביום
טוב, V'lo Olat chol b'Yom Tov, and you can't if it was
יום טוב Yom Tov you can't burn the fat from the previous
day on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So how can you burn the
fat of the קרבן פסח on the night of the 15th? That's
עולת חול. Olat chol. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, כבר רמיה ניהליה
רב אבא בר חייא לרבי אבהו, kvar ramya nihalei Rav Abba bar
Chiyya l'Rabbi Abbahu, this question was already asked from רב אבא בר
חייא Rav Abba bar Chiyya to רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, ושני ליה,
v'shani lei, and he gave the answer, הכא בארבעה עשר שחל להיות
בשבת עסקינן. hacha b'arba'asar shechal liyos b'Shabbat askinan. Here when the implication
of the פסוק, Pasuk, again, the simple sense of the פסוק Pasuk,
is it's really just talking about eating the meat throughout the night,
but the implication of the פסוק Pasuk the way you're reading it
that it's burning the fat throughout the night, that you're allowed to
do that, that would only be in a special case. What would
the special case be? That the 14th fell out on שבת. Shabbat.
So you're burning fat of a שבת Shabbat קרבן on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. It's funny, it's considered a שבת Shabbat קרבן even if
though its relationship to שבת Shabbat is just happenstance, right? It's not
like it's because it was brought because it was שבת, Shabbat, it
happened to have been
שבת. Shabbat. חלבי שבת, Chelvei Shabbat, but now it is fat of
a שבת Shabbat קרבן, and therefore קרבים ביום טוב, kreivin b'Yom Tov,
you can burn them on the night of the 15th even though
it is yesterday's קרבן because yesterday happened to be שבת. Shabbat.
But the לינה is leaving those חלב and אימורין overnight
to burn the next day?
No, burn it through the night. When it says הכל hacol הלילה
ילין, it means you can do it throughout the night.
So what was the problem with the כהנים coming and before they
said זריזין, zerizin, before they said the כהנים would be?
Oh, we're on a different דף daf now, but the זריזין zerizin
that issue was was that the כהנים will be careful, they won't
burn the stuff, and then the גמרא said okay, but if they're
not burning it they're not eating the meat, they're not eating the
meat, the owners aren't getting atonement, so you're back to the problem.
But I thought we just said דלינה d'lina is actually the burning,
right? Yeah. Is it the burning? So what would have been the
problem with their burning that stuff?
Oh because you can't burn on a קרבן that was brought after
the תמיד, meaning the תמיד. Okay, so anyway now we've got this
issue חלבי שבת chelvei Shabbat that how do you burn the fat
if you read the פסוק Pasuk that you can burn the fat
of the פסח throughout the night, then how does that work? Only
in a case where ערב פסח was שבת. Shabbat. אמר ליה, amar
lei, so he said back to him, משום דחלבי שבת קרבים ביום
טוב, mishum d'chelvei Shabbat kreivin b'Yom Tov, because of this rule that
you know you can't burn the fat on a weekday but you
could burn the fat on a you know you can't burn the
fat of a weekday קרבן but you can burn the fat of
a שבת Shabbat קרבן, אנן ניקו ונימא ליה בהאי קרא בארבעה עשר
שחל להיות בשבת הוא דכתיב? anan neiku v'neima lei b'hai kra b'arba'asar
shechal liyos b'Shabbat hu d'ksiv? So because you've got this problem, we're
going to say a פסוק Pasuk is talking, it's one thing to
say oh this ברייתא is talking in a very special situation, but
because you've got this problem we're going to say this פסוק Pasuk
is talking about this crazy case about only the case where שבת
Shabbat fell out on you know on ערב יום טוב? Erev Yom
Tov? Like why don't we just take the פסוק Pasuk at its
simple sense and do something with it rather than limit it in
this way? So אמר ליה, he said back to him, שבקינהו לקרא
דהוא דחיק ומוקי אנפשיה. shavkineihu l'kra d'hu dachik u'moki anafshei. Put aside
the פסוק, Pasuk that's difficult. ומוקי אנפשיה, u'moki anafshei, now I'm interested
here
what these last two words mean. How does your English translate those,
whoever has an English?
It forces itself to be interpreted this way.
Okay, is that what, Dovi, what do you have? You have an
English there or
no?
I'm interested because the way רש"י Rashi reads this, okay, is forget
the פסוק, Pasuk the פסוק pasuk is difficult, and as you just
read with the Artscroll, that's what
רש"י Rashi says, the פסוק pasuk forces
a because the פסוק pasuk is difficult because the פסוק pasuk, goes
against this principle, it sounds like you're burning the fat on the
night of the 15th, we know from another פסוק you don't burn
the fat of a weekday sacrifice, so the פסוק itself forces this
difficult explanation that it's talking only when שבת Shabbat precedes precedes יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So ומוקי אנפשיה, u'moki anafshei, the פסוק establishes it
on its own what is its narrow meaning. Is that what the
Soncino also says?
It says it's compelled to establish its
own particular case.
Compelled to establish its own particular case. Okay.
Why don't you just say that in the case of the פסח
offering the תורה Torah says it can be taken on שבת? Shabbos?
What?
I'm sorry, one more time?
I was just saying that the plain meaning.
Well, the plain meaning, well, that's exactly what he says. Well, first
of all, the plain meaning is we're talking about the meat, but
the other question could be exactly that. Exactly that! Why don't we
basically say that it overrides the general rule? And the answer is,
no, we don't want to have it override a rule, so we're
going to say it forces upon itself this narrow explanation. But I
think that this is this is very important because it gets to
this question of the sort of role, if you would, of you
know, of תורה שבעל פה. Torah Sheba'al Peh. And how much, like
you know, you have a simple פסוק which seems to say something,
and then we're going to say, yeah, but you know what, because
it doesn't make sense based on how we understand the other פסוקים,
pesukim it's going to force itself into this narrow explanation, which means
that, if you, one way of saying that is, in a contest
between the simple sense of the פסוק and what we think rationally
has to make sense based on consistency with other rules, you know,
the our sense of consistency is going to win out over the
simple sense of the פסוק and force it into this other explanation.
So, you know, it's pretty important in terms of that whole issue
about sort of the role of תורה שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al Peh
in understanding the פסוקים and taking the simple פסוק, a simple sense,
and forcing it into a narrow explanation. Okay.
Why don't we take the name, take the name of—